Guide to the Mary Ann Pickens' Lynn R. Lowery research collection, 1957-2007 MS 853
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Mary Ann Pickens' Lynn R. Lowery research collection
1957-2007
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Pickens, Mary Ann
MS 853
0.75 Linear Feet 2 boxes
This collection consists of research material created and collected by Mary Ann Pickens about Lynn R. Lowery.
Biographical / Historical
Mary Ann Barnes Pickens (1926-03-16 - 2013-08-11) was born in Jackson, TN. While it is unclear when she moved to Houston, TX, she did work for the Texas Business School in the 1980s. She also served as Treasurer for Pickens Medical Dist. Inc from 1980-1995. Because of her love of gardening, she was a member of various garden clubs, and was the Treasurer of the Greenwood Forest Garden Club. In 1999, she wrote the article, "Lynn R. Lowery, Plantsman." The majority of this archival collection focuses on her research regarding Lowery, which she used for her article. She also had a hand in creating the Lynn R. Lowery Arboretum at Rice University.
Lynn R. Lowery - Born in Mansfield, Louisiana, in 1917, Lynn R. Lowrey was a graduate of Louisiana State University in 1940 with a degree in horticulture. After serving four years in the US Army during World War II, he came to Houston in the 1950s to work with an established Houston firm, Teas Nursery. He soon opened his own nursery on Westheimer and was known for his unusual native plants. He landscaped many Houston homes and businesses and made many trips to identify and collect plants from Mexico. He received a grant to study certain plant species in China and was instrumental in providing funding for cancer research on Camptotheca trees. Lowrey was the recipient of many awards: the American Association of Nurserymen National Landscape Award, the Houston Botanical Society Environmental Achievement Award, the Houston Chapter of the American Institute of Architects Award, the Municipal Art Commission Award, and several plant conservation awards. He died in 1997.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of research material created and collected by Mary Ann Pickens about Lynn R. Lowery. It includes notes on interviews and copies of articles written by Lowery.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research. Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Richard Johnson in January of 2019.
Related Materials
Please see Rice University Lynn R. Lowrey Arboretum records, UA 276.
Index Terms
Subjects
Environment; Gardening -- Societies, etc.; Gardening; Women
Places
Rice University
Subjects (Persons)
Lowery, Lynn R.
- Series I: General Files
  - Anderson, Mike and Pat, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Articles by Lynn Lowery, 1958-1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1997-2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence - Hillier, Sir Harold, 1977-1981; 2004 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence - Lowery, Lynn R., 1957-1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence - McWilliams, Ed, 1998-2004 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Corresondence - Rice University, 2001-2003 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence - Tapley, Charles, 2000-2006 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cox, Paul, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Creech, David - China, 1989-1999 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Drummond, Marion, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Fairey, John, 1995-1998 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Fleming, William, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Founding document, 1997-2003-09-22 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Hill, Madalene, 1999-01-19 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Jones, Ann, 1992-1999 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Lowery programs / talks, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Lowery research, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Lynn R. Lowery Memorial Service, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Lynn R. Lowery, Plantsman" by Mary Ann Pickens, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - National Plant Society of Texas, 1977-1997 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Negatives, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - News clippings and articles, 1982-1998 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - News clippings - Arboretum, 1999-2006 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Parson, Jerry, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Peckerwood Garden Conservation Foundation Symposium, 2004-11-13 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Photographs, 1937-2004 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Plant orders, 1967-1968; n.d. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Plants, 1986-1999 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ross, Bob, 1999-2001 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Shoup, Mike, 2003-08-08 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Slides, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Southern Garden History Society, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Southern Garden Historical Society Annual Meeting, 1999-03-26-1999-03-28 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Speech card, 2001-11-09 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Stephen F. Austin State University Arboretum with notes by David Creech, 1987-1998 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Thomas, Nancy, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Welch, Bill, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Wiess College Grove Dedication, 2007-03-22 (Box 2, Folder 13)